See, this is a bonobo.
Ding!
I know you guys think I'm weird, and you're right.
You're right.
But I am so set-bent on you guys knowing more about bonobos
because it also ties into the way that white supremacy
ends up centering things and animals and people
for the wrong reasons.
There are four great apes.
Orangutans, gorillas, chimpanzees, bonobos.
Bonobos.
Now, when these white people came to Africa,
as they shouldn't have done,
and were all up in the mix, as they shouldn't have been,
and were studying things with their little myopic mindsets
of colonialism, they saw chimpanzees and bonobos.
And they were like, man, the chimpanzees,
they really, like, are angry, and, you know,
they are patriarchal, and they really, like,
are really scrappy.
The bonobos, they're pretty chill.
They're matriarchal.
They share.
This just doesn't really feel as interesting to us
because it doesn't feel as representative
of our human experience.
So because in their colonial minds
of raping and pillaging and taking,
they didn't see themselves represented in bonobos,
they didn't feel like they were as interesting,
and so that is why they were not centered.
But the bonobos, being the least known,
are also not getting the same amount of attention
as we have seen conservation apply to the other great apes.
We want to see the same thing for the bonobos.